In this lesson we're going to be learning about function return types in TypeScript.
We're going to know exactly how to define what a function returns, which is going to make
your code safer and then much easier to understand.
So every function can return a value.
TypeScript of course allows us to explicitly define the type of that return value.
This is called the functions return type.
By default, TypeScript's going to try to infer the type, which means we don't have to
explicitly set it.
This is going to try and do its best at guessing it.
But if you specify it, it's going to make your code much more predictable.
So let's just knock up an example.
So let's have a function and a simple one, like adding two numbers together.
A number and let's have B number.
Now we could just simply return a plus B. If we do that, of course, TypeScript's going
to have a look and work out that we are indeed trying to return a number.
So it's inferring this type.
But to make it more explicit, we can actually kind of enforce it by doing code on after
the function and then do number.
Of course, we have exactly the same thing, but we're just having TypeScript.
You know, we know what we're doing.
This is what we watch.
We want to return.
It's going to protect us.
So if we didn't try to return any other value, for example, a Boolean, then it's going
to say, I don't think so.
And it's going to return an error, protect us.
What happens if we actually didn't want to return anything at all?
So let's just have a function and let's say, call it discrete, take a name and inside
that function, we just want to just do a console log and say, hello, just return the person's
name, hello, dollar name.
Now, if you hover over it, again, the TypeScript is going to be smart and it's going to
figure out that we are not returning anything and it's going to assign the type void.
So void means we're not expecting any return value, which of course we're not because
we're just doing a console log.
Now, in any this case, we could try to be more explicit by doing colon and then void and
void means void of any return type.
Why bother to use explicit return types, if we could just let TypeScript food out ourselves.
Well, first of all, we are in a new world now, we're not using JavaScript, using TypeScript,
so we want to type everything we can because it makes our code self documenting.
As we go along, makes it very clear, including TypeScript and anyone looking at the code
that our intention is that we're not going to return anything and it's not just a mistake.
Also helps TypeScript to course catch errors and that makes our lives a lot easier.
And as I said, it will really improve code readability for other developers.
And this is of course going to have benefits if you're working on large projects or a member
of a team.
Of course, if you're just kind of throwing some code together as an experiment on your own
tiny project, then feel free to not bother to put any return types and that TypeScript
to it.
But again, I recommend perhaps even in doing small projects that you become disciplined,
that you make sure you always put return types on your functions so that when you
get a job and you're working with a bigger team, that you've already got those skills
and discipline in place.
Not just return one value, we can of course return multiple values, so we could do, for
example, we could return a string, we could also return a number if you want particular
one to two, and of course we could quite as well code do that.
Now one thing you could do is you could say I want to return void and I also could return
a string and TypeScript is happy because there could be a situation if you have some logic
in your code to return a string on the certain circumstances and lots of return a value
on the different circumstances.
So this is kind of valid.
Now here's some quick tips, so if you're writing some functions for a public API, then
always declare the return types because your clients are going to thank you if you're
very upfront with what you're actually returning.
Use void for any functions that just perform actions, perhaps examples are just like say
logging or the debugging purposes.
And definitely try to avoid relying on TypeScript's inference if you're writing some
complex functions because it may not always get it right.